Guide to A Brief History of Bladderball [Research Materials and Essay] by Sarah Hammond
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
A Brief History of Bladderball [research materials and essay] by Sarah Hammond
1879-2009
RU 1121
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(3 boxes)
The materials consist of research notes, copies of articles, correspondence, outlines, drafts, and other materials compiled by Sarah Hammond (Yale College, 1999) for her senior essay titled, "A Brief History of Bladderball."
Hammond, Sarah Ruth, 1977-2011
Biographical / Historical
Sarah Ruth Hammond (1977-2011) was born and raised in Oberlin, Ohio. She received her BA degree in 1999, and her PhD in History of American Religion in 2010, both from Yale University. As a Yale undergraduate, Hammond wrote her senior essay on the history of Bladderball, a game traditionally played by Yale students between 1954 and 1982, after which it was banned by the university's administration due to the raucous and sometimes disruptive nature of the game. Hammond received numerous awards as both an undergraduate and graduate student, including the Andrew F. Mellon Fellowship in Humanistic Studies; the Richard J. Franke Interdisciplinary Fellowship; and a Lake Doctoral Dissertation Fellowship from the Lake Institute on Faith and Giving at the Center on Philanthropy at Indiana University. She also worked for several years at the Yale Center for Interdisciplinary Research on AIDS. At the time of her death, Sarah Hammond was a visiting professor at the College of William and Mary.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mary and Steve Hammond, 2012.
Arrangement
Materials arranged as received.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
General
Forms part of Yale Record Group 49 (YRG 49), Papers and projects on Yale.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of research notes, copies of articles, correspondence, outlines, drafts, and other materials compiled by Sarah Hammond (Yale, 1999) for her senior essay titled, "A Brief History of Bladderball."
Hammond, Sarah Ruth, 1977-2011; Yale University -- Student life
- "A Brief History of Bladderball" essay, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Yale alumni phone interview notes, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Research notes, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Research materials
  - General, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alumni, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bladderball, 1999-2009 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The college experience, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - College folklore, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fraternities, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Halloween, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Yale as a community, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Yale folklore and traditions, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Yale Daily News
    - 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1878-1890 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1905 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1915 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1950s (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1960s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - WYBC broadcasts of Bladderball
    - 1967, 1 (Box 4)
      General
      This seems to be the item mentioned in Kevin Devoe's letter dated January 18, 2000 in box 1, folder 3.
    - 1968, 1 (Box 5)
      This seems to be the item mentioned in Kevin McKeown's letter dated January 21, 2000 in box 1, folder 3.